Guide to the Gay Cable Network Archives 1982-2001 MSS 231
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Gay Cable Network Archives
Bulk, 1984-2000
1982-2001
MSS 231
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
400.0 linear feet (254 Boxes)
Founded in 1982 by Louis P. Maletta, the Gay Cable Network was the premiere media chronicler of events and personalities of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) community for nearly two decades. GCN programming broadcast on public access television in New York City and other major cities worldwide.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections. Viewing access is available in the Fales Reading Room only. At this time, only three GCN programs (Pride and Progress, The Right Stuff, and Gay USA) are currently available for viewing. Please ask a Fales archivist for more information.
Arrangement
Pride and Progress / The Right Stuff / and Gay USA are the only programs with accessible viewing material at this time. Some programs remain unavailable due to tape deterioration. Each digital viewing file contains one broadcast program from each show.
Other GCN programs will be made available as they are preserved.
Scope and Content
Founded in 1982 by Louis P. Maletta, the Gay Cable Network was the premiere chronicler of major events and personalities of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) community for nearly two decades. Broadcast on public access television in New York City and other major cities worldwide, GCN covered key LGBT civil rights battles, five presidential conventions, as well as the AIDS pandemic and social protests often marginalized in the mainstream media. On televised programs like Gay USA, Pride and Progress, The Right Stuff, Men and Films, Candied Camera, In the Dungeon, and Lavender Health, GCN conducted numerous interviews with leading politicians, medical and educational professionals, entertainers, and social activists.
Materials currently available for viewing are restricted to three GCN programs, Pride and Progress,The Right Stuff, and Gay USA. Please ask a Fales archivist for more information.
Biographical Note
Under the direction of Lou Maletta, and broadcast on Manhattan Cable Television Channel 35, Gay Cable Network (GCN) began in 1982 and stopped production in 2001. GCN was the first network in the nation to openly appeal to a gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender audience. GCN initially broadcast a series titled "Men in Films," which explored the gay male image in media and male erotica, and the network soon evolved to host a wider variety of content, including news and current affairs programs which covered political developments affecting the LGBT community and the AIDS/HIV epidemic. Throughout its time, GCN provided coverage of the Democratic and Republican National Conventions, with on-floor correspondents interviewing candidates and delegates, as well as coverage of the 1987 and 1993 LGBT rights marches on Washington. A documentary aired on GCN, "Out in the 90's," earned the network a Special Recognition Award at the inaugural GLAAD Media Awards in 1990.
Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc..; Humm, Andy; Maletta, Louis P.; Northrop, Ann; Cable television; Gay activists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Gay liberation movement.; Gay men.; Gay rights |z United States.; Gays in popular culture.; Gays |x Political activity |z New York (State) |z New York.; Gays |x Political activity |z United States.; Lesbian, gay and bisexual studies.; Lesbians |z United States.; Video recordings |x Political aspects.; Video recordings |x Social aspects.
- Series X: Gay USA
  - Subseries A: Cablecast Programs
    - 1990 Vol. [VIII]
      - Gay USA No. 2, 1990 (Box 36, Media ID: 231.0564)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Available for viewing by appointment only.
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        Format: VHS
        TRT: [unknown]
        Scope and Content
        Program Content: GCN National Show: Parades
      - [1]--Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 2 [Air date: 7/5/1990] [2]--Pride and Progress (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0098)
        Currently not available for viewing.
        Format: 3/4 in. Umatic
        TRT: 00:59:00
        Program content: Parades
        Program Content: Unknown
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 3 [Air date: 7/12/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0099)
      - [1]--Gay USA, Vol. [VIII] Episode No. 4 [Air date: 7/19/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0100)
        COMMERCIAL: OutWeek Magazine
        1. Footage of the International AIDS Conference in San Francisco
        COMMERCIAL: 550-TOOL (8665), ONLY .10 MIN - .20 FIRST MIN
        2. Phil Zwickler, Editor of PWA “Newsline”, interviews Peter Staley and Garance Frank-Ruta, of ACTUP New York, regarding the International AIDS Conference in San Francisco.
        COMMERCIAL: Gay Men’s Health Crisis (GMHC), “The Time Is Now…Get the Facts”
        3. Footage of the 13th Anniversary Celebration of MECLA. Includes footage of Christopher McCauley; Sheila James Kuehl, of the So. Calif. Womens Law Center; and Dave [Pallone], gay ex-Major League Catcher.
        COMMERCIAL: The Monster, NYC club and bar
        4. Footage of the Human Rights Campaign Fund Gala with Joan Rivers
        5. Human Rights Campaign Fund “Washington Update” regarding the Americans with Disabilities Act, which would include individuals with HIV/AIDS. Includes interview with Karen Friedman, lobbyist.
        6. Lou Maletta interviews Robert Brading, Director of the Fund for Human Dignity, regarding a recent staff walk-out. Also includes footage of David Stickle, former staff member of the Fund, discussing the recent staff walk-out.
        7. “Naming Names”: Janet Rogers, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses a recent newspaper article regarding the Gay Officers Action League (GOAL).
        COMMERCIAL: Laser Medical Associates
        8. “Lavender Health”: Ron Vachon, Director of the Office of Gay and Lesbian Health Concerns, interviews Polly Thomas, M.D., Director of the AIDS Surveillance Unit, regarding recent HIV/AIDS-related statistics.
        9. Footage of play “Men of Manhattan”.
        COMMERCIAL: Brought to you in part by 550-TOOL (8665), ONLY .10 MIN - .20 FIRST MIN
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 5 [Air date: 7/26/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0101)
        1. Andy Humm discusses recent general events that relate to the LGBT community.
        2. Footage of Hon. David N. Dinkins, NYC Mayor, at the First Mayor’s Conference for Lesbian and Gay Press. Includes footage of Lou Maletta.
        3. Footage of ACTUP protest of President George Bush. Includes footage of Lou Maletta interviewing protest attendees.
        4. Footage of Human Rights Campaign Fund Dinner in Los Angeles. Includes footage of Karen [Ocamb], of GCN Los Angeles, interviewing Midge Costanza, Assistant to President Carter; [Jeannie Wolf, host]; [Tom Gingerella, chairperson]; and Tim McFeeley, Executive Director of the Human Rights Campaign Fund (HRCF).
        5. Footage of Grace Jones performing at the Palladium, to raise money for ACTUP and the Keith Haring Foundation. Includes footage of Lou Maletta interviewing attendee Robert Parker.
        COMMERCIAL: New Millennium Productions presents “Tarzana Queen of the Jungle”
        6. Lou Maletta interviews Marc Huestis, director, regarding his film “Men in Love”.
        7. Lou Maletta interviews Shirley [Purvitis], Indianapolis Police Department Liaison, regarding her position and responsibilities.
        8. “Naming Names”: Dr. Henry Yeager, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses recent homophobia in New York Magazine.
        9. “Lavender Health”: Frank Oldham Jr., Project Coordinator at [Men of Color AIDS Prevention Services (MOCA)], interviews Craig Harris, of Gay Men’s Health Crisis (GMHC), regarding HIV/AIDS in the black gay community.
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 6 [Air date: 8/2/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0102)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 7 [Air date: 8/9/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0103)
        1. Lou Maletta interviews Rick Panson, owner of Duplex bar, regarding the boycott of Miller beer.
        2. Lou Maletta interviews Dino Rossi, of ACTUP, regarding the boycott of Miller beer.
        3. Karen [Ocamb], of GCN Los Angeles, questions Reverend Louis Sheldon, Fundamentalist minister, regarding his tax-exempt status. Includes undercover footage.
        4. Karen [Ocamb] of GCN Los Angeles, interviews John Duran, Esq., Attorney at Law, regarding Reverend Louis Sheldon’s tax-exempt status.
        5. Footage of “Pink Panthers On The Prowl” event. Includes interviews with Gerri Wells, Coordinator of the Pink Panthers; Red Mahoney, Chair Christopher Street Festival; Dale, of the Pink Panthers; Byron, of the Pink Panthers; [Allen] Contini, victim of bashing; [Ron Gruenwald] of ACTUP and Queer Nation; and Mike and Tina, ‘Just visiting NYC’.
        COMMERCIAL: SF AIDS Foundation, “The Condom: Don’t leave home without it”
        6. “All About Women”: Rebecca Lewin interviews Marjorie Hill, NYC Mayor Dinkins’ Liaison to the gay and lesbian community, regarding her position and responsibilities.
        7. Karen [Ocamb] interviews John Duran, Esq., Mr. Christopher St. West, regarding a neo-Nazi group in Orange County called White Aryan Resistance (WAR).
        8. “Naming Names”: Karin Schwartz, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses the exclusion of gays and lesbians in a new promotion by American Express and Continental Airlines.
        9. “Lavender Health”: Frank Oldham Jr., Project Coordinator for [Men of Color AIDS Prevention (MOCA)], interviews Eric Perez, Community Associate of the (MOCA) Project, regarding a recent study on black men concerning AIDS prevention.
        10. Footage of the Gay Games 1990 in Vancouver, British Columbia
      - [1]--Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 8 [Air date: 8/16/1990] [2]--Pride and Progress (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0104)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 9 [Air date: 8/24/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0105)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 10 [Air date: 8/30/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0106)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 11 [Air date: 9/6/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0107)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 12 [Air date: 9/13/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0108)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 13 [Air date: 9/20/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0109)
        COMMERCIAL: 550-TOOL (8665), ONLY .15 MIN - .40 FIRST MIN
        1. Footage of victory party for Deborah Glick, Democratic nominee for NYS Assembly. Includes Andy Humm interviewing Deborah Glick regarding her political views.
        2. “All About Women”: Rebecca Lewin interviews Sandra Rovira, surviving spouse of AT&T employee Marjorie Forlini, regarding her lawsuit against AT&T regarding her denial of surviving spouse benefits.
        3. Clip of music video “Blood Bath” by Phranc, lesbian music artist. Introduced by Brandon Judell.
        4. Nicholas Schaeffner, Philip-Morris stockholder, discusses his letter to Philip-Morris regarding his family’s disapproval of the company’s support of Senator Jesse Helms.
        5. “Lavender Health”: Ron Vachon, Director of the Office of Gay and Lesbian Health Concerns, interviews Marjorie Hill, PhD, Director of the NYC Mayor’s Office for Lesbian and Gay Community, regarding the functions of her office.
        6. “Naming Names”: Dr. Henry Yeager, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses a recent article in Ebony magazine titled “An Honest Look at Black Gays and Lesbians”.
        7. Lou Maletta interviews Catherine Saalfield, Curator of the Lookout Lesbian and Gay Video Festival, regarding the festival. Includes clips of “Laws and Skin” by Chris Martin and “Degas of the B-Boys” by Matt Ebert.
        8. Barry Miller, of the Gay and Lesbian Switchboard, discusses the Fall Frolic Festival and Follies.
        9. Lou Maletta interviews [Matthew] Geller, Exhibit Curator of “From Receiver to Remote Control” at The New Museum of Contemporary Art.
        10. Lou Maletta encourages viewers to contact Richard Aurelio, President of Time Warner NYC, to give GCN more time to negotiate their contract.
        COMMERCIAL: Long Island Association for AIDS Care (LIAAC), for the second annual pledge walk
        11. Footage of Jack Hoffman in “Don’t Tell Mama”.
        COMMERCIAL: Brought to you in part by 550-TOOL (8665), ONLY .15 MIN - .40 FIRST MIN
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 14 [Air date: 9/27/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0110)
        Currently not available for viewing
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 15 [Air date: 10/4/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0111)
        1. Andy Humm discusses the demise of the Fund for Human Dignity.
        2. Interview: Ed Mickens, Former Consultant, discusses the demise of the Fund for Human Dignity.
        3. Lou Maletta discusses GCN’s move to a different channel at a different time.
        4. “All About Women”: Rebecca Lewin interviews Dell Richards, author, regarding her book “Lesbian Lists: A Look at Lesbian Culture, History, and Personalities”.
        5. Lou Maletta interviews Tim Sweeney, of Gay Men’s Health Crisis (GMHC), regarding his recent promotion to Executive Director from Deputy Director of Policy upon the resignation of Jeffrey Braff.
        6. Footage of the Greater Gotham Business Council forum on “The Media and the Community”. Includes footage of Susan [Chasen], Publisher at Visibilities Magazine; Lou Maletta, National Director of GCN; and Jean Sidebottom, Publisher at Sappho’s Isles.
        7. Lou Maletta interviews Michael [Farnham], artist, at The Right to Light fundraiser, regarding the lavender lights atop the Empire State Building in recognition of gay pride.
        8. Chris Burns encourages viewers to volunteer for his self-defense video in response to an increase in gay bashing.
        9. Lou Maletta interviews Georg Osterman and Everett Quinton, actors, discuss the drag version of “Camille” at The Charles Ludlam Theater (The Ridiculous Theatrical Company). Includes performance footage.
        10. Robert Patrick, playwright, encourages viewers to see his new play “Hello, Bob”.
        11. “Naming Names”: Karin Schwartz, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses a recent episode of The Marsha Warfield Show in which Warfield, the show’s host, promoted misinformation regarding the gay community.
        12. Bob Hope speaks out against anti-gay bigotry.
        13. “Lavender Health”: Ron Vachon, Director of the Office of Gay and Lesbian Health Concerns, interviews Ellen Rautenberg, Assistant Commissioner of the NYC Department of Health, regarding AIDS prevention in NYC.
        14. Additional footage of [“Camille”].
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 16 [Air date: 10/11/1990] (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0112)
        1. Raymond Jacobs, of the Young Adult Institute and the AIDS Advisory Council to the Board of Education, and Catherine Lynch, of the AIDS and Adolescents Network of New York and the AIDS Advisory Council to the Board of Education, discuss AIDS prevention.
        2. Footage of Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD) forum: “Gay Access to Cable”. Includes footage of Lou Maletta, National Director of GCN, and Robert Jacobs, General Council and Vice President of Time Warner City Cable Group. COMMERCIAL: Gay Men’s Health Crisis (GMHC), “The Time Is Now…Get the Facts”
        3. Nick Curto interviews David [Bear], President of [the Network], regarding the new Network Room at the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, & Transgender Community Center, also called The Center. Includes footage of Marjorie Hill, Lesbian and Gay Liaison to Mayor’s Office, giving speech thanking those who funded the Network Room.
        4. Lou Maletta interviews Odell Mays, Director of Information and Education at Identity House, and Kay Lockridge, Treasurer and Peer Counselor at Identity House, regarding their organization’s purpose as a resource for the LGBT community.
        5. Footage of Stop Jesse Benefit for N.C. Senate Vote 90. Includes footage of Robin Burdulis, Laura Wetzler, Greg Harris, and Laurie Anderson.
        COMMERCIAL: Music For Life, for benefit concert for the Gay Men’s Health Crisis (GMHC)
        6. Footage of memorial service for Ethyl Eichelberger, [actor and playwright].
        7. “Lavender Health”: Ron Vachon, Director of the Office of Gay and Lesbian Health Concerns, interviews Ellen Zaltzberg, Project Coordinator for the Lesbian Health Project, regarding the Project’s functions.
        8. “Naming Names”: Kirk-Evan Billet, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses the United States Navy regarding the expulsion of female officers who might be lesbian.
        9. Footage of The Flirtations, [an a cappella group].
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 17 [Air date: 10/18/1990] (Box 8, Media ID: 231.0113)
        1. Andy Humm discusses recent general events that relate to the LGBT community. Includes footage of Leonard Bernstein.
        2. Footage of “Should We Boycott Channel 13 (or support it?)” open forum at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center. Includes footage of Harry Chancey, Vice President and Director of Broadcast Center; Adrian Miller, of Queer Nation; Ann Northrop, activist and TV producer; and Fred Noriega, Director of Public Affairs Programming.
        3. Lou Maletta interviews Dr. Mary Ann Humphrey, Ed. D., author, regarding her book “My Country, My Right to Serve”.
        4. “All About Women”: Rebecca Lewin interviews Dolly Meieran and Stacey Mink, of Women’s Health Action and Mobilization (WHAM), regarding their organization’s functions as a reproductive rights group.
        5. Footage of National Coming Out Day forum at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center. Includes footage of Dr. Marjorie Hill, NYC Mayor Dinkins’ Liaison to the gay and lesbian community, and Gabriel Rotello, Editor-in-chief of OutWeek Magazine.
        6. [D. Isadore] discusses recent entertainment related events that relate to the LGBT community.
        7. Lou Maletta interviews Gary Bastian, President of the [Republicans for Individual Freedoms], regarding his group’s first time endorsement of a Democrat, Harvey Gantt, due to their strong opposition to Gantt’s opponent, Republican Jesse Helms.
        8. Lou Maletta interviews Alice Wong, Vice President of Parents FLAG (Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays), regarding her organization’s functions.
        COMMERCIAL: Njeri, age 11, talks about the Holocaust, in support of “A Living Memorial to the Holocaust Museum of Jewish Heritage”
        9. “Lavender Health”: Eric Perez, Community Educator at Men of Color AIDS Prevention Program [MOCA], interviews Reggie Williams, Executive Director of the National Task Force on AIDS Prevention, regarding his organization’s functions.
        10. “Naming Names”: Dr. Henry Yeager, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses recent comments made by Arsenio Hall, talk show host, for Us Magazine.
        11. Footage of “House of Field” at the Roxy.
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 18 [Air date: 10/25/1990] (Box 8, Media ID: 231.0114)
        1. Footage of the forum “What should the role of straight people be in a gay organization?” at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center. Includes footage of Andy Humm, forum moderator; Susan [Chasen], Editor of Visibilities Magazine; Jackie Bishop, Artistic Director and Founder of Mama Doesn’t Know Productions; Ann Northrop, activist with ACTUP, Queer Nation, and other groups; Rebecca Lewin, host of “All About Women” on the Gay Cable Network; and Lou Maletta, National Director of the Gay Cable Network.
        2. Footage of the Human Rights Campaign Fund Dinner from Oct. 20, 1990. Includes footage of Hon. David N. Dinkins, Mayor of NYC; Craig Davidson, recipient of the 1990 Visions & Victories Media Award; and Hon. Gerry E. Studds, [politician].
        4. Lou Maletta interviews [Kenneth Cooke], Executive Director of the Justice Project, and Carroll Hunter, former Deputy Director of Guidance and Counseling [Services] for the NYC Department of Corrections, regarding gay life in the prison system.
        5. Lou Maletta interviews Larry Schneider, co-owner of Julia, regarding his gay restaurant on the Upper West Side.
        6. Footage of press conference, “Bias Crime Statistics Released at City Hall, NYC”. Includes footage of [Frances Kunreuther], Executive Director of the Hetrick-Martin Institute, and Deborah Glick, Democratic Candidate for NYS [Assembly].
        7. Footage of “Allan” discussing his coming out story [at the National Coming Out Day forum at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center].
        8. “Lavender Health”: Eric Perez, Community Educator at Men of Color AIDS Prevention Program [MOCA], interviews Reggie Williams, Executive Director of the National Task Force on AIDS Prevention, regarding his organization’s functions.
        9. “All About Women”: Rebecca Lewin interviews Dr. Nancy Goldner, Ph.D., CSW, of the Psychotherapy Group of Park Slope, regarding child sexual abuse.
        10. “Naming Names”: Karin Schwartz, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses a recent episode of “Married…With Children” involving gay themes. Includes television show footage.
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 19 [Air date: 11/1/1990] (Box 8, Media ID: 231.0115)
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 20 [Air date: 11/8/1990] (Box 8, Media ID: 231.0116)
        1. Footage of Andy Humm at celebration for Deborah Glick’s election to NYS Assembly. Includes interviews with Dr. Marjorie Hill, NYC Mayor Dinkins’ Liaison to the gay and lesbian community; [Katherine Brady], Correspondent for “Out in the 90’s”; Dave Taylor, former President of Gay and Lesbian Independent Democrats (GLID); and Deborah Glick.
        COMMERCIAL: WBAI Holiday Crafts Fair
        2. Lou Maletta interviews [Yvegenia Debryanskaya], Editor of Tema and member of MULH, and Steve Nelson, regarding the first gay and lesbian rights newspaper in Russia.
        3. Lou Maletta interviews [Kenneth Cooke], Executive Director of the Justice Project, and Carroll Hunter, former Deputy Director of Guidance and Counseling [Services] for the NYC Department of Corrections, regarding gay life in the prison system.
        4. Lou Maletta interviews Sergeant Edgar Rodriguez, Deputy Director [of] Manhattan South, and police officer Louise Gomez, Deputy Director [of] Queens, regarding the Gay Officers Action League (GOAL).
        5. Footage of the “Safe Sex Six” trial regarding six individuals who protested anti-gay measures of the Catholic Church at St. Patrick’s Cathedral.
        6. “All About Women”: Rebecca Lewin interviews Ann Northrop, activist and one of the “Safe Sex Six”, and attorney Lori Cohen, regarding the trial.
        7. “Lavender Health”: Frank Oldham Jr., Project Coordinator for [Men of Color AIDS Prevention (MOCA)], interviews Eric Perez, Community Educator at Men of Color AIDS Prevention [MOCA], regarding community changes since AIDS was first discovered.
        8. “Naming Names”: Dr. Henry Yeager, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses a recent Newsday cover story regarding the murder of James Zappalorti.
        9. GCN Special Report: Trial of Safe Sex Six, Verdict Delivered November 8, 1990.
        10. Interview: Vito Russo, as part of Stonewall Remembered, 1989, discusses his experience at Stonewall.
      - Gay USA, Vol. [VIII], Episode No. 21 [Air date: 11/15/1990] (Box 8, Media ID: 231.0117)